welcome back to the channel
like I said last week we've got visitors
and one of them is a plant-based eater
so we have done last week we did the
Haagen-Dazs chocolate Midnight Cookies
in plant-based form
this week
it's the chance for the lemon to shine
so we're going to make a like a lemon
meringue
pie ish kind of ice cream I don't know
whether I'm going to put the biscuit
base in I haven't decided yet
so what we're going to do is
get started with this stuff
and
this stuff
[Music]
add some of this stuff
see where we end up
[Music]
squeak
so
where do we start with plant-based ice
creams
same way you'd start any ice cream
really that's kind of how you need to
approach it but you just need to think
about similar things a little more
carefully so
if you use an ice cream calculator
you're going to struggle with your milk
solids non-fat that isn't a thing you
can put your ingredients into a
calculator and it will show milk solids
non-fat
that's not there so you've got to make
sure that you're getting enough fat and
enough sugar
to create that luxury mouthfeel
stabilizing plant-based ice creams is
pretty important because
there's a lot of free water in all of
these ingredients
but
it's not rocket science
so I've got a recipe
in front of me that I've just kind of
fumbled my way through on dream Scoops
calculator
I'll put a picture up on the screen so
you can see and
what we've got here is 250 grams this is
of our milk which is the oat milk 450
grams of the cream which is this silk
it's 33 dairy free whipping cream
140 grams of sugar 30 grams of dextrose
and our stabilizers obviously if you
can't put in skim milk powder
so we're gonna probably up the
stabilizers to a little bit more
to help boost the stability and the
mouthfeel of this ice cream
so let's weigh out our ingredients so
we're just going to put our pan on our
scales
and start adding it all in
doesn't smell good
I'll get 450 of our cream
[Music]
there we go
whole thing
and we'll tell that and then we'll add
in our
of our oat milk
there
dextrose and sugar so
let's get a spoon
dextrose is 30 grams
30 grams
and a lot of sugar
so because we're going to use a
stabilizer
my
assistant
if anyone knows me I love this stuff
it's a really really good mix
um
they do I think now ship internationally
according to the website
special ingredients if you're watching
if you want to sponsor this channel I
would love it anyway
we're going to stabilize so we're going
to need to put some of that in our
sugars and mix it up so let's get a
little pop
stuff
lots of stuff turned up a nice box of
ice cream stuff turned up undamaged
in our Goods last week so nice
these really help this this is my little
mini scales for measuring stabilizers
really really helps
so we want to add
how many sugars
140 grams of sugar
so
start
so there's 120
[Applause]
and the last 20 we can get rid of these
and we'll take our little mini scales
put that on there and we're going to add
in a little more than I would normally
so
give it a little stir
just because I can
two grams
foreign
nicely mixed and combined
in it goes
let's get this on hob
and now
lemon
we're just gonna stir all our
ingredients together on the hob just to
get the sugars melted and then we're
going to bring it up to
about 70c
70 to 75c
and that's to activate that stabilizer
so I will stand here and do this and
I'll see you in a bit
whilst our mix is warming up we're going
to take our microplane or mini
grater or whatever you've got to hand
and we are going to take our lemon and
get the lemon zest into the pan to start
releasing that flavor
[Music]
we're just starting to get some steam
coming up now so I've got my laser
thermometer go in and we're just going
to keep an eye on the temperature so
we're a kind of 65 degrees here
so like I said before I say I say this
in quite a few videos if you don't have
one of these you kind of don't need one
you just need to look at when that steam
starts to come off the top
and then keep it there for a couple of
minutes just agitate it a little bit
make sure that nothing sticks
and then when you get to
that 70 degrees
you know you're good to go we are about
there
so we're going to turn this off move it
onto a Coral Park hob
because we're going to get it in a bowl
[Music]
so that's one lemon zest one lemon's
worth of zest in there if you wanna
boost that without adding any more lemon
zest I like lemon zest in the ice cream
and a nice little texture thing to
you can add lemon extract
I've got some in the cupboard I might
add some on this I haven't decided
[Music]
now let's
add another lemon zest
and go natural
[Music]
all right let's get all that in
that lemon is gonna really jump out now
we're gonna
leave that
with a lid on
[Applause]
in the fridge overnight
it's the next day the ice cream base has
been in the fridge overnight we need to
prepare a couple of other things so for
this as it's a lemon meringue pie kind
of thing
we are going to need
pie crust
and the marshmallow fluff
so back in England pie crust for things
like this for home Bakers is normally
made with
digestive biscuits
warm up
397.
um
in North America it's
graham cracker
also 397 same
400 grams
so 400 grams there we go so that's how
much it cost use whichever one I am
gonna go with
graham cracker because
we're in Canada
we're going to make
pie crust by adding the plant-based
butter
and that and we're going to just put it
in the oven for
five or ten minutes just to warm that up
let's start mixing let's get a bowl
some kind of spoon
I'm not even gonna measure this
smells quite similar
that's right
I'm gonna wing it
[Applause]
it's probably about 200 grams
something like that
and now we're going to take some of our
butter
put a little pot
and a spoon
and we're gonna melt the butter
in the microwave
how much do you think we need
all right what's that
some you don't want too much butter
when doing something like this
about 30 seconds 30 40 seconds something
like that you don't want too much butter
because when you put this in the oven if
you've got too much butter then the
butter will boil and it will kind of
separate your base so you just want
enough melted butter to bring it
together
so it can clump
so we're going to put our butter
into there
let's say it was probably about the 70
grams 70 80 grams
and we're just gonna
combine the butter with our graham
cracker just put a little bit more in
there
okay that's kind of the texture that
we're looking for it looks like sand
kind of semi damp sand and when you when
you press it against the side of the
bowl it just starts to maintain that
shape
much liquid
and your butter will boil
so we're going to line this we're going
to get this mix
into here
and then just press it down
until it fills
the pan
I will put all the ingredients and
recipe in the description below so you
know exactly how much of everything I've
used
press it down quite hard
so you get this dense
layer of your
biscuit crumb
you can use a glass to do this or
a bit of wood or rolling pin or whatever
you've got to hand I'm just using the
spoon because
it's only a small pan isn't it there we
go so
we're going to pop this in the oven at
325 for about 10 minutes
and whilst that is doing its thing we're
gonna make some
vegan marshmallow fluff this is the
first time I've
done it over here and I'm gonna
go down the aquafaba route
a
friend of the channel
said that
Dave had great success using aquafile
but I couldn't do it back in England it
just wouldn't whip up now whether that's
something to do with the brand of
chickpeas I bought I don't know but
we're gonna try
again so here we go
so what do we need we're going to need
some
aquafaba
chickpea liquid
chickpea
liquid I'm going to use some sugar
um some cream of tartar some vanilla
and most recipes don't call for this but
the golden syrup and glucose syrup if
you do the standard non-plant based
marshmallow fluff that I've used in
quite a few of my recipes it's
impeccable that has the golden syrup in
it so we're going to add it into this
and try and recreate the same kind of
thing
so first off we want
120 grams
of our
chickpea come on let go
liquid
there we go 120 grams of chickpea look
let's put this in the fridge
foreign
looks like egg white
definitely
definitely different to the chickpea
liquid that I used back in England so
that's a good start I guess
what do we need now we need 150 grams of
our sugar we'll measure that the end
because we're going to add it down a
lime we need our cream of tartar
oh God broke this door
we need vanilla
is that the horrible looking vanilla yes
and
what
stuff
so
two grams of cream of tartar
people don't like how I say cream of
tartar apparently it annoys some people
so
harder
do I know how much two grams of this is
it is that much
two grams of cream of tartar
we're gonna put in our
50 grams
of golden syrup
this is great
this tastes just like
UK was it Titan La it's good stuff
and our vanilla I've got this so we're
gonna use it
there we go
vanilla
it said
half a teaspoon in this original recipe
I've probably put in double that
because I don't want any potential Taste
of this chickpea stuff so we're going to
get this running and then when it comes
up to like a soft Peak we're going to
start in our sugar
[Music]
oh
foreign
[Music]
okay
our screen machine is in
let's get that
pre-chilling there's lots of stuff going
on
let's see how we got on I tell you what
though
considering my previous experience back
in the UK which was
terrible it didn't do anything this is
really good it's um
fluffed up nice
[Music]
still doesn't quite have you know what
I'm just gonna have more vanilla
the vanilla from
Walmart just doesn't cut it
there we go
strong stuff
homemade vanilla
triple fold
let's get that incorporated
now we're talking
that
um
that vanilla was made
with a mixture of
rum and whiskey
if you're interested in knowing how to
make your own extracts of all different
flavors
then
let me know in the comments
and we can do some videos
right a bit more space back so that's
good
don't want to waste that
let's get
our ice cream out the fridge
and we'll get it churning
here we go
now the only concern I have
is the color
because
this
foreign
smell is is great I mean really really
nice and strong
the oils have come out of that zest
but the color is pretty unappetizing
it's a it's a plant-based thing
you don't get that nice
White
[Music]
base
I'm gonna I'm gonna add some yellow
you don't have to do this bit
um I just bought some this morning
it looks kind of
got look at that stuff
yeah it just doesn't look an appetizing
color I don't want to put too much in I
just wanna
I just want to take the edge off that
brownie dirty white color
and make it just slightly yellow
don't want to go too mad but I want a
bright yellow
I might just done
that's better
we're just starting to touch into yellow
color all right we're not going too mad
again like I said don't have to use this
don't have to do this
but I'm like a traditionalist with ice
cream I'm making mint ice cream I want
it to be green
I don't want white mint ice cream I know
a lot of people ran to the middle it was
amazing I don't want the green food
coloring yeah but you'll eat all the
sugar and everything else that's in
there but you don't want the food
coloring
so
let's pour this into a machine and get
it done
and I shall come back in about 15
minutes when we'll be ready to load up
the tub of all our goodies
and then slain entry
all right we've just turned off the
freezer Port part of the machine let's
try our
yep nice
all right we've got a little cubes of
pie crust
we've got our meringue
which
we gotta look at that
sticky
it needs that vanilla
it really really needs up
punch of vanilla
use more
use more vanilla extract in your
plant-based
vegan marshmallow fluff and that
golden syrup
it makes the world of difference
if you don't add golden syrup to
marshmallow fluff you don't get that
silky smooth kind of sticky texture
which you want from fluff
just becomes like Swiss meringue which
is lovely and you can actually use Swiss
meringue for this if you know if you're
not going the whole plant-based thing
add that
add that in there right stop talking
we're gonna take our little tub
I got a big tub off camera that's going
to be loaded up we're going to put a few
pieces of our crumb in there
we're going to take a spoon of our
marshmallow
and we're gonna
load up
uh ice cream
like so and we're just gonna
turn it over so if if you want to take
like I do take your ice cream out the
machine just a minute or two earlier to
make that easy then do that okay don't
feel you have to leave it in there until
it's exactly the right
temperature you can take it out a couple
of minutes early it won't affect your
ice cream at all
more fluff in there
I'm gonna put two dollops
don't scrimp
and a really gorgeous smelling lemon ice
cream
going in there
oh this is going to be good
and we're just going to turn it over
one more time
like that
get the lid on
oh yeah
in the freezer and we'll come back
probably
tomorrow
here we go I knew it would have been
Days by the time I got back around to
trying this
ice cream but that's what happens when
you've got people around
anyway let's dish some of this lemon
meringue pie plant-based lemon meringue
pie ice cream and see what it
takes
[Music]
all right
foreign
[Music]
the lemons over here taste and smell
very different to the lemons back in the
UK obviously it's a different type I
don't know what type it is but something
to note
the
plant-based marshmallow fluff has worked
well it's held together well in the
freezer
we're gonna go for
ice cream and fluff
[Music]
biscuit base the graham cracker biscuit
base is perfect really nice
buttery kind of flavor obviously not not
real butter Plum based butter
the marshmallow fluff held up really
well in the freezer it didn't hold up in
the fridge
that's
something to note I guess because the
sugars started separate in
the fluff you can emit the
golden syrup or corn syrup if you want
that's
would it help maybe sometimes sugars do
just leech out of marshmallow fluff well
I don't know why it does it sometimes
and not others if you know that then let
me know in the comments because I would
rather it didn't happen
the ice cream has got a nice flavor it's
subtle it's not a bitter lemon it's
quite a nice light lemon
the little editions of
the zest in there is really nice get a
little bite of you know lemon zest in in
your Spoonful I really like that some
people don't like lemon zest in their
lemon ice cream so if you don't like it
just strain it out the flavor will still
be there
all in all not bad it's a little it's
got a touch of ice in there so I don't
know whether that's something to do with
cream because the cream was crap
it was the Silk plant-based 33 whipping
cream tasted hideous on its own in the
previous video I'll put a link below
but it's got a really weird smell tasted
texture and consistency there's nothing
about it I like if you're gonna make
plant-based stuff especially more
in Canada anyway
go for their half and half it's so much
better it has such a
more promising result there's no ice
with there it tastes better it's got a
better texture and consistency yeah
avoid the the silk 33 because it's
rubbish
but all in all I think that's another
successful plant-based ice cream if you
want to see more then let me know in the
comments what flavors you want to see
and I'll do my best to make them so
thanks very much for watching don't
forget to like And subscribe and I'll
see you next week
[Music]
foreign